Ronald Harmon Brown Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ronald Harmon Brown Papers 1992-1996
MSS85311
Brown, Ronald Harmon, 1941-1996
4,000 items
29 containers plus 1 oversize
11.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
U. S. secretary of commerce and lawyer. Government documents, briefing books, topical files, newsletters, reports, speeches, photographs, trip itineraries, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and miscellaneous material relating to Brown’s service as a cabinet member during the Bill Clinton administration.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Brown, Ronald Harmon, 1941-1996.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-
Organizations
National Information Infrastructure Advisory Council (U.S.); National Institute of Standards and Technology (U.S.); United States. Department of Commerce.; United States. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.
Subjects
Executive departments--United States--Reorganization.; Exports--United States.; Foreign trade promotion--United States.; Information networks--United States.; Science and state--United States.; Technology and state--United States.; Telecommunication--United States.
Places
United States--Commerce.; United States--Commercial policy.; United States--Economic policy--20th century.; United States--Foreign economic relations.
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Ronald Harmon Brown, U. S. secretary of commerce, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Alma Arrington Brown, and his children, Michael Brown and Tracey Brown between 2006-2010.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Audiocassettes and VCR tapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Ronald Harmon Brown Papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1941, Aug. 1 Born, Washington, D. C.
1962 Graduated, Middlebury College, Middlebury, Vt., and married Alma Arrington
1963 1967 Served in U. S. Army
1970 J. D., St. John's University School of Law, New York, N. Y.
1968 1979 Lobbyist and deputy executive director for programs, National Urban League
1979 1980 Deputy campaign manager, Edward Kennedy presidential campaign
1981 1985 Deputy chairman and chief counsel, Democratic National Committee
1988 Campaign manager, Jesse Jackson presidential campaign
1989 1992 Chairman, Democratic National Committee
1993 1996 U. S. secretary of commerce
1996, Apr. 3 Died in airplane crash, Dubrovnik, Croatia
Scope and Content Note
Ronald Harmon Brown (1941-1996) was a lawyer and Democratic Party operative who managed presidential campaigns for Edward Kennedy and Jesse Jackson and served as chairman of the Democratic National Committee. These papers relate entirely to Brown’s term as United States secretary of commerce during the Clinton administration. The papers span 1992-1996, ending when he died in a plane crash while on a mission to Croatia. They treat Brown’s death and legacy as well as his efforts to expand American exports and work with agencies such as the National Information Infrastructure, National Institute of Standards and Technology Programs, and National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. Featured also are congressional relations including legislation to dismantle the Department of Commerce and his trips and missions in the United States and to foreign countries.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material as received.
Container List
- Aerospace Industries Association, secretarial meeting with executives, 1993 (Box 1)
- Automotive industry and the Advanced Technology Program, 1995 (Box 1)
- Certifications (Box 1)
- Chicago Manufacturing Center, Chicago, Ill., 1994 (Box 1)
- Chronological office file, 1994-1996, (26 folders) (Box 1)
- Commerce People, newsletter, 1994 (Box 1)
- Commerce Works!, 1995 (Box 1)
- Congressional hearings (Box 2)
  - Briefing books, 1995, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Chronological file (Box 2)
    - 1993 (Box 2)
      - Feb.-Mar., (4 folders) (Box 2)
      - Mar.-June, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1994, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1995 (Box 3)
      - Jan. (Box 3)
      - Mar.-Oct., (7 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1996 (Box 5)
- Death of Brown, 1996, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Department of Commerce, budget and finance, (1 folder) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Reinvention (Box 6)
    - Approach to reinventing governmen (Box 6)
    - Reinvention activities (Box 6)
    - Reinvention laboratories (Box 6)
    - Reinventing permission slips (Box 6)
- Export growth (Box 6)
  - Aerospace Industries Association board of governor’s meeting, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Aerospace trade mission directories, 1993-1996 (Box 6)
  - Africa trade policy (Box 6)
  - Africa trip, 1995 (Box 6)
  - African-American Institute, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Akayev, Askar, president of the Kyrgyz Republic (Box 6)
  - American Business Centers (Box 7)
  - Americas Business Forum (Box 7)
    - Cartagena, Columbia, 1996, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Denver, Colo., 1995 (Box 7)
  - Baltimore, Md., Enhanced National Export Assistance Center Network, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Big emerging markets, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Brazil, memorandum of understanding (Box 7)
  - Brazil Roundtable, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Brazil-United States Business Development Council (Box 7)
  - Business America, 1996 (Box 7)
  - CABNIS Award (Box 7)
  - Caribbean Business Development Council (Box 7)
  - Central Asia Business Development Conference, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Commercial Development Mission to Sub-Sahara Africa, 1996, (1 folder) (Box 7, Box 8)
  - Congressional letters, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Cooperation agreement between the United States and Chile, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 8)
  - Cote D’ Ivoire (Box 8)
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Dakar, Senegal, conference, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Denver, Colo. summit, Western Hemisphere Trade and Commerce Forum, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Environmental technologies (Box 8)
  - Export finance programs (Box 8)
  - Gore-Chernomyrdin Commission (Box 8)
  - Indian-American newspapers, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Indian trade mission, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Indonesia-Malaysia trade mission (Box 8)
  - Middle East ambassador’s tour, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Minority business matchmaker delegation, Mexico, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Minority trade missions (Box 9)
    - Canada (Box 9)
    - Caribbean (Box 9)
    - Mexico (Box 9)
    - South America (Box 9)
  - Mission to Columbia, Panama, and Nicaragua (Box 9)
  - Mission to Bosnia and Croatia (Box 9)
  - Mission to Brazil, Argentina, and Chile (Box 9)
  - Mission to Third African American Summit, Germany (Box 9)
  - Muenster conference, 1996 (Box 9)
  - Multilateral Development Bank office, 1994 (Box 9)
  - National travel and tourism strategy, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Northern Ireland AMBIT program (Box 9)
  - Paris Air Show, Paris, France, 1993, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Presidential trade and investment mission to South Africa, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Presidential trade mission to Brazil, Chile, and Argentina, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Press releases, 1994-1995 (Box 10)
  - SABIT Exchange, 1994 (Box 10)
  - San Antonio, Tex., Border Conference, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Speeches, 1995 (Box 10)
  - St. Louis, Mo., outreach event, 1995 (Box 10)
  - State trade directors (Box 10)
  - Textile and Apparel Roundtable (Box 10)
  - Tourism Policy Council Meeting, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Tourism Policy Council, strategy, 1995 (Box 10)
  - Trip to California, 1995 (Box 11)
  - United States Commercial Centers (Box 11)
  - United States Export Assistance Center, New York, N.Y., 1995 (Box 11)
  - United States-Argentina Business Development Council (Box 11)
  - United State-China, “Framework Agreement” (Box 11)
  - United States-Kazakistan Business Development Committee, 1995 (Box 11)
  - United States-Panama Business Council, 1996 (Box 11)
  - United States-Russia (Box 11)
    - Joint commercial tax dialog, 1996 (Box 11)
    - Joint statement regarding medical industries (Box 11)
    - Miscellany (Box 11)
    - Partnership for Economic Progress (Box 11)
    - Spring business development mission, notebook, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - United States-South Africa Binational Commission, 1996 (Box 12)
  - United States-South Africa Business Development Committee, 1994 (Box 12)
  - United States-South Africa Business Development Council, 1995 (Box 12)
  - United States-South Africa Conference on Democracy and Economic Development (Box 12)
  - Uruguay Round (Box 12)
    - Opportunities for U. S. Industries, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - State opportunities reports (Box 12)
    - State reports (Box 12)
      - Alabama-Montana (Box 12)
      - Nebraska-Wyoming (Box 13)
  - West-East Conferences of Ministers of Economy, Industry, and Trade, second, third, and fourth conference, (3 folders) (Box 13)
- Foreign Direct Investments in the United States, 1993-1994 (Box 13)
- G-7 Ministerial Conference on Information Society, 1995 (Box 13)
- Global Information Infrastructure: Agenda for Cooperation, 1995 (Box 13)
- Information Infrastructure Task Force, 1993-1995, (3 folders) (Box 14)
- Japan, (3 folders) (Box 14)
- Leadership, Department of Commerce (Box 14)
  - Chronology of Clinton administration’s leadership in South Africa under Brown, 1994 (Box 14)
  - Congressional letters, Export Assistance Center openings, 1995 (Box 14)
    - Ann Arbor, Mich. (Box 14)
    - Atlanta, Ga. (Box 14)
    - Austin, Tex. (Box 14)
    - Boston, Mass. (Box 14)
    - Charleston, W.Va. (Box 14)
    - Columbia, S.C. (Box 14)
    - Columbus, Ohio (Box 14)
    - Dallas, Tex. (Box 15)
    - Denver, Colo. (Box 15)
    - Greenville, S.C. (Box 15)
    - New Orleans, La. (Box 15)
    - Pontiac, Mich. (Box 15)
    - Portland, Maine (Box 15)
    - Harlem, N.Y. (Box 15)
    - Long Island, N.Y. (Box 15)
    - New York, N.Y. (Box 15)
    - Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 15)
    - Richmond, Va. (Box 15)
    - Sioux Falls, S.Dak. (Box 15)
    - St. Louis, Mo. (Box 15)
    - Toledo, Ohio (Box 15)
    - Westchester County, N.Y. (Box 15)
  - Congressional outreach (Box 15)
  - Congressional testimony, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Dismantling legislation, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Economic accomplishment report, draft, 1994 (Box 16)
  - Foreign-Trade Zones Board, 1993 (Box 16)
  - Message to staff regarding dismantling (Box 16)
  - Minority business development mission to Ecuador and Chile, 1996 (Box 16)
  - Newspaper articles regarding Brown (Box 16)
  - Press releases regarding dismantling (Box 16)
  - Press release regarding minister counselor posted to South Africa (Box 16)
  - Salute to American fashion designers cohosted by Secretary and Mrs. Brown (Box 16)
  - Softwood lumber, United States-Canadian agreement (Box 16)
  - Staffing changes, memorandum, 1996 (Box 16)
  - Woodrow Wilson Fellowship, 1996 (Box 16)
- Malcolm Baldridge National Quality Award, 1994 (Box 16)
  - Award criteria, 1994-1996, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Baldridge Award ceremonies, photographs and press releases, 1994-1996 (Box 16)
  - Education pilot criteria, 1995 (Box 16)
  - Health care pilot criteria, 1995 (Box 16)
  - “The Malcolm Baldridge National Quality Award and ISO 9000 Registration,” article, 1993 (Box 17)
  - “The Malcolm Baldridge National Quality Award Concept: Could It Help Stimulate or Accelerate Health Care Quality Improvement?,” article, 1994 (Box 17)
  - Profiles of winners, 1995 (Box 17)
  - “Study finds ‘quality stocks’ yield big payoff,” newspaper clipping (Box 17)
  - “Succeeding with Baldridge Award,” leaflet, 1996 (Box 17)
- Manufacturing Extension Partnership, 1995-1996 (Box 17)
- Miscellany, 1994-1996 (Box 17)
- National Information Infrastructure Advisory Council (Box 17)
  - Kickstart Initiative: Connecting America’s Communities to the Information Superhighway (Box 17)
  - Meetings (Box 17)
    - 1994 (Box 17)
      - Feb., (2 folders) (Box 17)
      - Mar.-Sept., (6 folders) (Box 18)
      - Oct.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - 1995 (Box 19)
      - Jan.-Apr., (4 folders) (Box 19)
      - June-Aug., (5 folders) (Box 20)
  - Reports, 1995-1996, (2 folders) (Box 20)
- National Information Infrastructure, Progress Report, 1993-1994 (Box 20)
- National Information Infrastructure, universal access (Box 21)
- National Institute of Standards and Technology Programs (Box 21)
  - Advanced Technology Program, 1994-1996, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - Assessment panel reports, 1993-1995, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - Building and Fire Research Laboratory, 1995-1996 (Box 21)
  - Delivering Results: A Progress Report, 1995 (Box 21)
  - Guide to NIST (Box 21)
  - Information Infrastructure: Reaching Society’s Goals, 1994 (Box 21)
  - Innovation in the Japanese Construction Industry, a 1995 Appraisal (Box 22)
  - Network Brokers Handbook, 1995 (Box 22)
  - NIST Industrial Impacts, A Sampling of Successful Partnerships, 1995 (Box 22)
  - Publications and studies produced by others for NIST (Box 22)
  - Putting the Information Infrastructure to Work, 1994 (Box 22)
  - Rates of Return from Investments in Technology Infrastructure, 1996 (Box 22)
  - Rationale and Preliminary Plan for Construction and Building, 1994 (Box 22)
  - Technology and Economic Growth: Implications for Federal Policy, 1995 (Box 23)
  - Visiting Committee on Advanced Technology (Box 23)
    - The Advanced Technology Program, 1993 (Box 23)
    - Annual reports, 1992-1996, (4 folders) (Box 23)
    - Congressional testimony by chair, 1994 (Box 23)
    - International Standards Issues, 1993 (Box 23)
    - Meeting of chair with Brown, 1994 (Box 23)
  - White Papers Prepared for the White House–Construction Industry Workshop on National Construction Goals, 1994 (Box 23)
  - Working Conference on Global Growth of Technology: Is America Prepared?, 1995 (Box 23)
- National Medal of Technology ceremony, photographs See also Oversize (Box 23)
- National Telecommunications and Information Administration, 1995 (Box 23)
- National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (Box 23)
  - Marine Sanctuary, magazine 1995 (Box 23)
  - Miscellany (Box 23)
  - National Weather Service (Box 24)
    - Elrod, Jack, Mark Trail cartoon panels about NOAA weather radio, undated See Oversize (Box 24)
    - Nexrad radar system, 1995, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 24, Box 25)
  - NOAA press releases, 1993-1996 (Box 25)
  - NOAA Report, 1993-1995 (Box 25)
  - Photographs of Brown at NOAA functions, 1993-1994, (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Space Systems/Loral, Brown visit, 1993 (Box 25)
- National Technical Information Service (Box 25)
- Newspaper clippings, (1 folder) (Box 25, Box 26)
- North American Free Trade Agreement, 1993 (Box 26)
- Pace Setter, newsletter, 1995 (Box 26)
- Patent and Trademark Office, 1995-1996 (Box 26)
- Photographs (Box 26)
  - Combined Federal Campaign, 1996 (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - Race for the Cure (Box 26)
- Positive news stories about Department of Commerce (Box 27)
- Printed matter (Box 27)
- Speeches and statements, 1993-1996, (3 folders) (Box 27)
- Sustainable development, expanding exports of U. S. environmental technologies, (4 folders) (Box 28)
- Trade Promotion Coordinating Committee, 1993 (Box 28)
- The “Tech Team” (Box 28)
- Trips and missions (Box 28)
  - 1993, (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - 1994 (Box 29)
    - May, (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - June-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 29)
  - 1995, (2 folders) (Box 29)
- United States-Israel Science and Technology Commission, 1993-1994 (Box 29)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - National Medal of Technology, photograph (Container 23) (Box OV 1)
  - National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, National Weather Service, Mark Trail cartoon panels by Jack Elrod (Container 24) (Box OV 1)